#大家好 今天我帶兄弟們去摘野果
Hi everyone! Today I'll pick the wild fruits with my buddies.
#哇 這裡有一個
Wa! Here's one!
#這裡有一個 這個香藤子哦
Here's a, well, "xiang tengzi" (untranslatable wild fruit)
#嚐一下
Let me try.
#很不錯哦
It's really not bad.
#它這個品種就是這樣的 不是很紅
That's the species here. They're not really that red,
#黃黃的 你看
but yellowish brown, look!
像那個 血絲一樣的 (註︰這個不明白，他想說流出來的血絲，還是微血管的血絲)
It's like, blood veins.
血絲裡面的那個果肉
Under the blood veins, is the pulp.
#這個要摘掉 不摘掉會壞掉的
It needs to be picked. Otherwise it would be rotten.
#來 吃啊
Come on! Take it!
#來來來來來
C'mon, c'mon, c'mon!
#哇
Wa!
#這個也是大的
This is also large.
#嗯 阿欽
Um! Qin!
#阿良 這個很好吃的 你拿著
Liang! This is really tasty. Take it!
#你看 這裡好多黃牛哇
Look! Here're a lot of cattle.
#它們把路都堵住啦
They're blocking the way.
#我們站在旁邊 讓它從這裡過
Let's keep on one side, and let them pass on the other side.
#從這邊走 這邊上走
Walk on this side, along the edge!
#你看 終於發現那兩個黃的哦
Look! Finally, I found two brown wild melons.
#兄弟贊助了一個這個 夾果子的
My buddy sponsored this, eh, for picking fruits.
#我就不用爬樹啦
Then I don't need to climb the trees.
#這個 挺方便的這個
It's ah, it's quite a useful tool.
#你看 這申那麼長
Look! It can become that long.
#還可以繼續伸長
It can still be further extended.
#哈哈哈哈 有用有用
Ha ha ha ha, useful, useful!
#可以
Not bad!
#你看 這個
Look! This is...
#掉下來啦
I've cut it!
#你看
Look!
#掉在這裡啦
They're here.
#哇
Wa!
#這一個
This is,
#很靚哦
beautiful!
#坐地上來把它吃了再說
Let me sit down here and finish it first.
#外面好多人啊
There are so many people outside.
#哇 這個 你看
Wa! This is, look!
#太美味啦
It's simply delicious!
#嗯
Um!
#看一下上面還有沒有
Let me see if there are still any up there.
#這個
This is,
#這個給你吃 這個
this is for you, this one.
#要到裡面吃 吃啦 再出去哦
Stay here while eating. Finish it before you go out.
#那麼多人
There are so many people.
#哇 這裡好多哇 都是青的 都還沒熟
Wa! Many are still green, not yet ready.
#等下次過來摘
Let's come again next time.
#光這裡都能摘半個牛皮袋呀
Just the wild melons here can fill up half a bag.
#這一顆[SIC]樹
Just this tree
#慢一點哦
No hurry!
#你看 這裡有一個
Look! Here's one.
#看到沒有 這個就比較紅的
Can you see? This is more red.
#你看這個
Look at this one!
#哇 這個好紅的
Wa! This is really red.
嗯
Um!
#味道不錯
It tastes not bad!
#啊 給你吃 這個
Ah! This is for you. This is,
#最大的
the largest one.
#你看
Look!
#這個都還沒熟 還好青啊
This is still not ready. It's very green.
#去年這個時候都被鳥吃完啦
The fruits were all eaten by the birds around this time last year.
#現在 你看
But now, look!
#一樹都是 好多青的
They're all over three. Many are still green.
#硬邦邦的
As hard as stone.
#我們去另外一條 另外一座山里面
Let's go to another, onto another hill.
#我們去另外一座山裡面看一下
Let's have a look on another hill.
#看一下 遠 那邊的有沒有熟
Let's see, furth... if the fruits are ready there.
#它應該是陽光照射的[SIC]久一點點的地方 就快熟一點點
Perhaps the fruits are growing faster at the places with better sunshine.
#你這看個 夠大吧
Look at this one. It's rather big, isn't it?
#跟我的手那麼大 這個
It's as big as my hand.
#你看 這不知道是誰做的記號
Look! Somebody has put a mark here.
#兩個
Two
#這記號把它塗掉
Let me cross out the mark.
#不知道誰做的記號
I don't know who made it.
#啊 把這個記號塗啦 就是我的啦
Ah! I've crossed out the mark. So it's mine now.
#你看 這樹頂上有一個那個
Look! At the tip of the tree, there's a, well,
#鐵老虎
"iron tiger" (black tiger fruit).
#兩個哦一個小的一個大的
There are two, one small and one big.
#就那裡
Just over there.
#我爬上樹上去把它摘下來
I'll climb the tree and get it.
#這個 樹又
The...tree is,
#太大啦
too big.
#看著來 這個是
Watch out! Here're,
#剪刀來的
the scissors.
#嗯 放 你要放掉
Um! Off, off you hands.
#好 放
Alright! Off!
#來喲 剪了
Oh! Got it!
#哦
Oh!
#哎喲
Ayoooo!
#1斤啊
One good whole pound!
#不熟就浪費了
It would be a waste if it's not ready yet.
#看一下
Let me have a look.
#哎喲
Ayohhh!
#拿我看一下
Come and let me have a look!
#砸到我的腳了
It hit my foot!
#你看 這個小的
Look! The small one is,
#這個營養不良的
suffering from malnutrition.
#這個大的
And this is large.
#把它掰一個下來吃一下
Let me get a piece and try.
#哎呀
Haiya!
#那麼緊
It's so hard.
#嗯 味道很不錯哦
Um! It tastes really not bad.
#它吃(的)話就吃那麼一點點
The edible part is just a bit here.
#兩個籽都那機大
Both seeds are that large.
#我們這邊叫
Here it's called,
#把這個叫做鐵老虎
it's called iron tiger here.
#是啊 這個有點緊
Yup! It's a bit hard.
#好像不是很熟
It's not really too ready.
#嗯
Um!
#好香哦
The scent is great!
#裡面的果肉特別香
The scent of the pulp is really good.
#這個是酒飯糰
This is "jiu fantuan" (tiger fruit, lit: wined rice ball)
#我們管這個叫大酒飯糰 你看
It's called large "jiu fantuan" here, look!
#一個大 一個小
Big and small
#那麼小 差那麼遠
It's so small. What a difference!
#來 嚐一下 一人拔一個
Come on! Have a try! Everyone get a piece.
#來啊
Yeah!
#你看 這個肉
Look! The pulp is,
#很靚的哦
really beautiful!
#晶瑩剔透
Crystal clear
#它這個 這個味道很好 很香的這個味道
It has a, a great taste, and a great scent.
#它的肉就那麼一點點的
The pulp is just a tiny little bit.
#就這一點點
Just a bit
#把這一點點吸掉就好啦
Suck here, that's it!
#你看 這個狐狸桃
Look! This is "fox fruit".
#我們這邊
Here we,
#我們這邊叫狐狸桃
here we call it "fox fruit".
#其實這是獼猴桃 跟獼猴桃一模一樣的 (註︰雖然「獼猴桃」不是特別方言，但想突然兩種動物，所以加上"Monkey fruit")
In fact it is "monkey fruit" (kiwifruit). It's exactly the same as "monkey fruit",
#但這個是野生的
except that this is wild.
#還沒熟哦
It's still not yet ready.
#還沒熟也可以吃的
But it's still can be eaten.
#就是有點酸
It's just a bit sour,
#有點澀
a bit bitter.
#吃起來
But in fact,
#味道很不錯
it tastes really not bad.
#好酸
Very sour!
#這個打過霜之後才可以吃的
It's edible only after frosting.
#現在還不能吃
It's now inedible.
#不是不能吃 就是太酸啦
It's not really inedible, just too sour.
#沒甚麼味道 現在還聞不出來
Not much smell. Can't really smell anything at this moment.
#等熟了之後就可以
When it's ready,
#把這個
we can,
#摘下來直接扔到嘴巴上一口就把它悶了
pick it, throw into the mouth, and swallow.
#很好吃的
It will be really tasty!
#還沒熟
But not now.
#剛剛我們看了好多都是青的 還沒熟
We've just seen that many fruits are still green, can't be picked.
#我們再過半個月過來
We'll come again in a fortnight,
#那個帶 帶多幾個袋子過來
with, ah, with some bags.
#現在
Now,
#都沒熟
not yet ready.
#好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
#回家啦
Let's go home!
#沒心情
No mood!
#回家餵竹鼠
Go home and feed my bamboo rats.